<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Obedience and submission A sermon preached at St. Sauiours-Church in South-warke, at a visitation, on Tuesday, the eigth [sic] day of December: anno Dom. 1635. By Iohn Fealtly.</title>
            <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00607</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101903</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837706</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837706</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00607)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 793:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Obedience and submission A sermon preached at St. Sauiours-Church in South-warke, at a visitation, on Tuesday, the eigth [sic] day of December: anno Dom. 1635. By Iohn Fealtly.</title>
                  <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[adger],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2046:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2046:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBEDIENCE AND SVBMISSION.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. SAVIOURS-Church in <hi>South-warke,</hi> at a <hi>Viſitation,</hi> on <hi>Tueſday, the eigth day of</hi> December: <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1635.</p>
            <p>By IOHN FEATLY.</p>
            <q>Obedientia non ſervili metu, ſed charitatis affectu ſervanda eſt: non timore poenae, ſed amore juſtitiae. <bibl>
                  <hi>Greg.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> Mor.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. B. Anno Dom.</hi> 1636.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2046:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2046:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF OBEDIENCE <hi>AND</hi> SVBMISSION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hebrews 13.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Obey them that have the rule over you; and ſubmit your ſelves.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vthority is the <hi>baſis</hi> of regularity; and this of peace: for confuſion raves in diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and the want of ſubmiſſion is the ground of contention. 'Tis thus in Civill; 'tis likewiſe in Eccleſiaſticall governement: <hi>Religion</hi> is forced into a melancholike dejection, if not ſupported by Lawes provided for her content. Shee's at leaſt <hi>obſcured</hi> where not <hi>countenanced</hi> with <hi>authority;</hi> and languiſhes in a conſumption where ſhe deſpaires of regard. She requires power, but ſuch as either findes, or inforces <hi>obedience:</hi> She triumphs in <hi>authority;</hi> but ſuch as we finde aſcribed to the <hi>deſtinies, Fata volentem ducunt, nolentem
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2046:3"/> trahunt:</hi> gently leading the obſequious; but by violence drawing the refractory mutiniers. For 'tis but idle aire that is articulated in commiſſions, and not neceſſitate's <hi>obedience. Superiority</hi> degenerates into the miſerie of a <hi>Hieroglyphick,</hi> if it knowes no more than a titular <hi>Chimaera,</hi> and becomes the ſad Embleme of its neglected ſelfe. 'Tis at moſt but a Mercuriall ſtatue, only pointing out, not ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the way.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould I looſe my time in the treatie of ſuch a no-thing? For ſo it is. Compariſons are <hi>Relatives;</hi> and ye know the Canon in Logick, <hi>Poſito vno Relatorum, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur &amp; alterum.</hi> Relatives are Twins, and derive their being from the ſame inſtant. There cannot be a <hi>great,</hi> but there muſt be a <hi>little:</hi> there cannot be a <hi>ſuperiour</hi> unleſſe we grant an <hi>inferiour:</hi> the <hi>higheſt</hi> muſt have a <hi>loweſt:</hi> and how can this bee granted in policie without <hi>obedience.</hi> Otherwiſe 'tis a <hi>parity,</hi> not a <hi>government;</hi> 'tis a giddie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, not a well-ordered command. <hi>Religion</hi> hath her juſt policie. She proceeds by rule. <hi>Authority</hi> ſpeakes, and <hi>obedience</hi> anſwers. Thus does the Common-wealth, thus does the Church too triumph though ſhe's <hi>militant.</hi> Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the LORD'S ſake, whether it be to the King, as ſupreme, &amp;c. 'Tis S. <hi>Peters</hi> in his 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> and 13. <hi>Verſ.</hi> There's the prerogative of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and the loyalty of the Subject. It is the ſame too (although ſubordinate to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſtie) in the Church, according to S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the warrant of my Text, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Too curious a diviſion may offer violence to my Text. For mine owne part I affect not their courſe, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour rather the magnifying of their wit, than the true divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2046:3"/> of the matter. The words are plaine; my diviſion ſhall imitate. The ſentence is a precept (properly, rather than counſell) to obedience. Herein obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1 The Object of our duty: <hi>viz. They that have the rule</hi> over us.</item>
                  <item>2 The Subject, or matter of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, turning upon two hindges, <hi>ſcil.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>Submiſsion.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in their order; and firſt of the Object of our dutie, or perſons to be obſerved, <hi>Thoſe that have the rule over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe.]</hi> A number excludes a Deitie; but power inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates it. Where ſhall I begin then to ſeeke my Object, but there where I finde the centre of command? I muſt look up firſt to thy Throne, O GOD, and acknowledge with ſubmiſſion, that thou haſt the rule over me. I muſt acknowledge further too:</p>
            <p>(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes the heathen Poet.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homer.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Odiſſ.</note>) Although thy Throne be far, yet thy power is neere for my ſalvation, if it may ſtand with thy gracious pleaſure. And not ſo onely, but yet further too I muſt determine with the ſweet<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec.</hi> in Ep. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ad <hi>Lucilium.</hi>
               </note> Philoſopher, that <hi>Propè es, mecum es, intus es:</hi> Thou art neere me in thine ordinances, if I obey; thou art with me in thy care, if I ſubmit: thou art in me by thy Spirit, if I humbly receive thee. Let me begin then with my GOD; and ſo let me end too, ſince he's the <hi>Alpha</hi> and the <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>beginning</hi> and the <hi>end, Apoc.</hi> 1.8. We had had no creation but by his power; we had had no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes without that creation: wee ſhould have had no Lawes without thoſe Kingdomes: and we can have no Magiſtrates to execute thoſe Lawes, but by his election: ſo our Apoſtle tels us, <hi>There is no power but of God, Rom.</hi> 13.1. 'Tis ſtrange to me therefore (when I conſider that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2046:4"/> this GOD is but one) that the Heathen ſhould dreame of a plurality. Yet tis true: yee have read it, and I have knowne it among them. 'Tis ſtrange too (when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>infinity</hi> of this my GOD) that the ſottiſh <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> ſhould ſtile their <hi>Nero</hi> God, whoſe wandering car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſe ſo long ſince travelled in the bellies of the Wormes. But 'tis more ſtrange when I reade of Chriſtians, that ſtile a mortall man <hi>Dominum Deum noſtrum.</hi> Yet this is true; ye may finde it among the Papiſts. They might have had more pretence for it (I confeſſe) had they at firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled the <hi>Papacie</hi> to it, and not the Man; for to that they aſcribe a kinde of immortality. Againe, 'tis ſtrange too (when I ponder upon the <hi>Vbiquity</hi> of my GOD) that a man could live which would denie a Deitie. Yet ſuch there is, I muſt, I will beleeve it, for 'tis canonicall, <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God, Pſal.</hi> 14.1. But where is no God? Thou Foole, if this night he condemne thy ſoule, thou wilt finde that there is a God. He's in that heart which denies him, either in mercie to convert, or in judgement to confound. Behold then, here's the ground of our object, GOD; for the higheſt powers that the Sunne gazes upon, receive their command from his divine Ordinance. He commands, and Kings obey; for by him Kings reigne, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. Kings command, and we obey; 'tis our Apoſtles injunction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. Thus muſt ſubjects, thus muſt inferiours, ſubject, ſubmit to their Kings; to their Superiours, <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>for</hi> his ſake who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, becauſe (ſayes my Text) they <hi>have the rule over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who are theſe which <hi>have the rule over us?</hi> We may be unjuſt in our obedience if we ſubmit to a Vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Bleſſed be <hi>God</hi> (my beloved brethren) we can have no ſuch pretence for rebellion. 'Tis firſt our dread <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2046:4"/> to whom (without ſo much as the leaſt ſuſpition of doubt) we muſt humbly, and heartily ſubmit with the greateſt induſtry of obedient loialty: And let the hearts of thoſe Traitors that conſpire diſloialty, by a juſt <hi>Prolep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> teach them their fate, in being the burning tormentors of their diveliſh ſelves. But muſt we obey none elſe? Yes, his Miniſters of juſtice too, or elſe we are Rebels. His Eccleſiaſticall Iudges; for thoſe he appoints for the ſweet harmonious government of the Church, by religious and juſt diſcipline. His Civill Magiſtrates too; for they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter juſtice in the weale-publike. All theſe muſt be conſcionably and carefully obeyed, for they <hi>have the rule over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Multiplicitie of expoſitions hath begotten a pluralitie of opinions; ſome making <hi>Soveraigne Supremacie</hi> the aime of my Apoſtle; others only the reverend Clergie. I will not neglect either; but give me leave to begin with the firſt, the beſt, The King. <hi>Obey the King,</hi> for he hath the rule over us.</p>
            <p>Next under <hi>God,</hi> his Majeſties authority is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and publiſhed by the Clergie: ſo ſaies the firſt Canon. 'Tis my loialtie to ſubſcribe to it; and 'tis my joy that your reverend ſelves are the juſt witneſſes of my <hi>canonicall obedience.</hi> 'Tis our dutie in generalll to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it; and it ſhall be my forwardneſſe. Yea, and 'tis fit for my Text too in part; for this is the expoſition of<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Aretius</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zuing.</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Zuinglius:</hi> the words of the former are theſe; <hi>Praepoſitos hîc Magiſtratus intelligo, aut certè Seni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores qui populo praeſunt, &amp; in caetibus fidelium authoritate an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecellunt.</hi> The other is not ſo confident in his opinion, and therefore ſayes only, <hi>Videtur referendum eſſe ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistratus obedientiam.</hi> The reaſon of both is rendered by them both, <hi>Quia de Miniſtris priùs jam egit verſu ſeptimo.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2046:5"/> I muſt confeſſe, that I ſubſcribe not in judgement to this their opinion, but yet 'twill advantage me to make uſe of their miſtake. S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſeemes at firſt to be the Author of this opinion, <hi>ſed parum commodè</hi> ſayes<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hyper.</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Hyperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> and his reaſon is double; <hi>ſcil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe the Hebrewes at that time had few or no Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Magiſtrates that profeſſed the faith; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, cruelly endeavoured their violent ſuppreſſion. But (by his leave) if the ſenſe would beare it, the exhortation were juſt, to admoniſh the people to obedience, even to <hi>them,</hi> ſince they were ordained their Magiſtrates: as ye ſhall heare hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe in the inſuing words, the Apoſtle tels them, that they <hi>watch for their ſoules. Atqui Magiſtratus civiles</hi> (ſayes <hi>Hyperius) non incumbunt propriè ſaluti animarum; ſed tuentur ea quae ſunt ſalutis externae, &amp; corporalis:</hi> But (ſayes he) 'tis the property of the civill Magiſtrate, to care for the externall government of the bodie, and not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy himſelfe about the affaires of the ſoule. That's his reaſon indeed. But we know it otherwiſe (bleſſed be our Almighty Protectour) in theſe flouriſhing Kingdomes. For he that is the <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> and Supreme, as well in Eccleſiaſticall, as Civill matters, hath, doth, and I pray God long he may, <hi>Watch over our ſoules,</hi> although not by immediately exerciſing the function of a Miniſter; yet mediately executing his ſacred and religious juſtice and providence, by the learned and vigilant Lords, both ſpirituall and temporall. Yea, let me go a little further yet too; and with humbleſt thankfulneſſe let me acknowledge, that <hi>immediately</hi> alſo he watches over us, by his care of the Church, and preſerving it from injuries by his royall protection. Thus doe we juſtly acknowledge that he is our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our Prince, to whom of right it belongs to have the rule over us.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2046:5"/>
            <p>Our ſecond ſort of Expoſitors, will have the word to intend our reverend Prelates: and juſtly. They are ſtiled by
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Tremellius,</hi> and <hi>Arias Montanus; Duces,</hi> our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Beza; Ductores,</hi> our Leaders.</item>
                  <item>3 The vulgar Latins, <hi>Leo Iuda, Iohan. Benedict. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſien.</hi> and <hi>Stephanus; Praepoſitos,</hi> which</item>
                  <item>4 The <hi>Rhemiſh Teſt.</hi> engliſhes, <hi>Prelates.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Fabritius,</hi> and <hi>Sebaſtian Caſtalion; Gubernatores,</hi> our Governours.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Praepoſitos vocat paſtores, &amp; Epiſcopos,</hi> ſo ſayes <hi>Cornelius a Lapide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Paſtores, &amp; Gubernatores;</hi> ſayes <hi>Hemmingius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Praelatos, &amp; Superiores;</hi> ſo <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Eccleſiae Paſtores,</hi> ſaies <hi>Hyperius:</hi> And he renders the reaſon why theſe are meant, and not the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; <hi>Cum enim inter Hebraeos variae ſubinde ſererentur opiniones, &amp;c.</hi> The Hebrewes were contentious in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of their opinions: Some denying CHRIST to be GOD: ſome rendering him <hi>not;</hi> and ſome, but equall with <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſome contending for the ceremonies of the Law: and laſtly ſome too, hammering out of their owne braines other ſuch doctrines of errours; and yet every one boaſting of his opinionative learning, and vaunting of his skill in the expoſition of the Scriptures. In the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of theſe diſturbances a cure was provided. They had a <hi>Prelate</hi> to appeale unto, whoſe care it was to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile their differences. Our Apoſtle therefore endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſatisfaction, admoniſhes them to obedience to thoſe <hi>that have the rule over them.</hi> This I conceive to be proper. We'l follow this expoſition, and according to their Titles we'l enquire into their Offices.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2046:6"/>
            <p>Ye have heard that they are our Captaines, Leaders, Governours, Prelates, which are here intended. They are thoſe in every Countrey, to whom by a juſt power is committed the government of the Church. Not any ſchiſmaticall Sectarie here; nor any ſelfe-conceited railer beyond the Seas. Not the grave-bearded Browniſts; nor the down-look't Separatiſts; nor the diſorderly Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts. Not the Apron preachers of ſome Sects; nor the illiterate, pettiſh Baulers among others. Theſe are the Authors of diſtraction, not order; and the ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to mutinie and rebellion, not the compoſers of differences intended in my Text. Such as theſe have formerly ſwarmed in this our Kingdome; but (God be bleſſed) the care of thoſe <hi>who watch over us,</hi> hath corrected the furie of their publike diſorder. Did ye but heare them in their Conventicles in thoſe Countries where they have gained their freedome, you would wonder that men ſhould be ſold to ſuch folly. Ye know what once did ſave the Capitoll,
<q>Sollicitive Canes, canibuſvè ſagacior Anſer.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe we can ſcarcely imagine worthy to be ranked with them, becauſe (on the contrary) they are Traitors to ours. Ye would hardly beleeve how gravely they will ſpeak their undigeſted crudities; and father their contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions upon the bleſſed Spirit. They will maintaine a precedencie indeed; but 'tis preſerved in each perſons opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his particular ſelfe. Every man among them is beſt, although none be good: all are Lords; none Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Had they but ſo much of reaſon as they want of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, I doubt not, but they would eſpie their own enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. But ſo long as they hug themſelves in theſe their vanities, give me leave to determine them to be none of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> my Apoſtle meanes.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2046:6"/>
            <p>In our Church they are the moſt reverend Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the right reverend Biſhops, and thoſe whom they appoint for the preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſcipline in our flouriſhing Church. 'Tis confeſſed that ſome will ſtorme at my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to whom the name of a Biſhop is a ſtrong purgation. But them I remit to their owne <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Geneva:</hi> and if want of imployment be the cauſe of their exception, let them confer about a better expoſition of S. <hi>Iohn, Rev.</hi> 9.3. See the fate of error, how it concludes in ignorance, and where contention is grounded upon a diſturbed paſſion, how does it vent it ſelfe in termes appropriated to follie? If Learning and Religion be growne ſo much out of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as that Academicall Degrees, and Eccleſiaſticall Orders render us Locuſts, we'l wiſh that they may once be baniſhed into their wits, or elſe remit them to their <hi>Fornace.</hi> They will be angry (I beleeve) if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort it upon themſelves:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin.</hi> nat. hiſt. tom. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> I reſolve therefore not to ſtile them Locuſts, but me thinks they come very neere the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis</hi> in <hi>Plinie,</hi> which ſo long as it is in the fire, it liveth: but if it chance to leape forth of the Fornace, and to flye far into the aire, it dieth. Their beginning is the <hi>Ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus</hi> of an unhallowed zeale; I meddle not with their end. Theſe notes are truly <hi>Nigro carbone notandae:</hi> I leave them therefore to the judicious cenſure of Authority.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſtrange too, that their great Abbettour ſhould ſo much miſtake; as to ſay, that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza</hi> in annot in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Gradus Epiſcopalis eſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Apoſtolicae ignotus.</hi> Certainly in this, the fury of his paſſion quarrelled with his learning, and thence he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this raving <hi>phrenſie.</hi> Otherwiſe I cannot imagine how it will be maintained, that becauſe our Apoſtle uſes the plurall numher in my Text, we may therefore conclude with him, <hi>Nondum illum gradum Epiſcopalem fuiſſe in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam inuectum.</hi> He proceeds to ſpeake what (for his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2046:7"/> owne ſake) I bluſhed at when I read it, <hi>A quo certè Satan ſuam Oligarchiam auſpicatus eſt, quae in tyrannidem illam Antichriſtianam evaſit, &amp; nunc quoque Eccleſiae inſtauratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem remoratur.</hi> I will not engliſh it for their ſakes whom it leaſt concernes; nor confute it, leſt by that they conject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure at what I conceale. Such opinions as theſe have ſpawned ſedition and often howled and yelled in our Mother the Church. But alas, did their maintainers but conſider the burden of theſe our <hi>Captains,</hi> our <hi>Leaders,</hi> our <hi>Governours,</hi> our <hi>Prelates;</hi> I preſume their contention would be changed into pitty; and their oppoſition would end in obedience to theſe that <hi>have the rule over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would ye know their <hi>burden?</hi> Let my Apoſtle ſpeake it in the enſuing words, <hi>They watch for your ſoules as they that must give an account:</hi> And let<note n="*" place="margin">Cor. a Lapide <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cornelius a Lapide</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the words, <hi>Quantumuis honoris, reverentiae &amp; obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae deferas praepoſito, nunquam onus, &amp; periculum quod ipſe pro te ſuſcepit adaequabis;</hi> All the honour, reverence, and obedience which ye performe to your <hi>Prelates,</hi> will never countervaile their burden, and danger. Or elſe here <hi>Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingius</hi> his concluſion, <hi>Graviſsimum, &amp; laboris, difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiſque pleniſsimum eſt paſtorum officium:</hi> the miniſteriall function is both weighty, and laborious even in inferiors, what then may we deeme it to be in ſuperiours?</p>
            <p>Would you know their care? Let<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fulg.</hi> in Verba, ipſi enim per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigilant, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſpeak it. <hi>Soliciti ſunt,</hi> ſayes he,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Praedicando.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Bonum exemplum praebendo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Exterior a providendo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>They are carefull in their
<list>
                  <item>1 Doctrine.</item>
                  <item>2 Coverſation.</item>
                  <item>3 Hoſpitality.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Hence our Countrey-man the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nic.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gorran. in verba qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi rationem reddituri.</note> 
               <hi>Dominicane</hi> concludes, that <hi>curae praelatorum requiritur;</hi>
               <list>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2046:7"/>
                  <item>1 <hi>Solicitudo, quia pervigilant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Magnitudo, quia rationem reddituri.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Multitudo, quia pro animabus veſtris, non tantùm pro ſuis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Aquinas</hi> upon the place obſerves, that becauſe they are <hi>Paſtores,</hi> therefore they doe, or ought to imitate the Shepherds in <hi>Luke</hi> 2.8. Which at the Nativity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, did both <hi>abide in the field,</hi> and alſo <hi>watch</hi> over their <hi>flocks</hi> by <hi>night.</hi> Yee heare their <hi>burden</hi> and <hi>care;</hi> and (if as yet yee are not ſnatched up into admiration) I ſhall heighten you with that of S.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome, Miror ſi potest ſalvari aliquis rectorum:</hi> But let<note n="*" place="margin">G. Eſtius <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gulielmus Eſtius</hi> qualifie him: <hi>Haec dicit reſpiciens ad multitudinem eorum qui per am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitionem ſeſe conjiciunt in illam tanti momenti functionem:</hi> for God forbid that the admiration ſhould extend to a univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality without any exception, <hi>Nam legitimè vocato, &amp; fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, atque ex charitate ſacrum illud munus exercenti, qualis fuit ipſe Chryſoſtomus, periculum eſſe non poteſt,</hi> ſayes the ſame <hi>Eſtius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye have heard their <hi>labour:</hi> or elſe let<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de civ. Dei.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeake it, <hi>Epiſcopus nomen eſt operis.</hi> Wherefore (my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) as ye are
<list>
                  <item>1 Souldiers, ſo yee muſt obey your reverend <hi>Prelates,</hi> for ye heard that they are your <hi>Captaines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 As ye march in your ranks towards the Kingdome of Heaven, ſo ye muſt obſerve them, for they are your <hi>Leaders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 As ye live in the bleſſed time of a flouriſhing Church, ſo ye muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto them, for they are your <hi>Governours.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 As ye are in ſubjection, ſo ye muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2046:8"/> obey them; for they are <hi>Praelati,</hi> they have the <hi>rule over you;</hi> ſo ſayes my Text. I will conclude this point with that of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in locum.</note> 
                     <hi>Malum eſt ubi nullus eſt principatus, &amp; multarum cladium extitit occaſio:</hi> which I will engliſh thus: The want of Epiſcopall juriſdiction, hath proved the cauſe of many a bloudy contention. Or I wil conclude with that of <hi>Cornelius a Lapide, Cum tantum ſit onus praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiti,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cor. a Lap. <hi>in locum.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>promptè illi obedito, nè ſi ſis dyſcolus, &amp; inobediens onus ejus aggraves, ſub quo ipſe gemat dum cogitat, quòd pro tuâ in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedientiâ, &amp; malitiâ Deo rationem reddere debet.</hi> Let the weight of the <hi>Prelates</hi> function, be a forceable argument to perſwade you unto a ſubmiſsive obedience. 'Tis moſt juſt, 'tis moſt neceſſary: my Apoſtle commands it; <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves:</hi> which is the ſecond Generall, <hi>The duty injoyned:</hi> viz. <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> and <hi>Submiſsion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Vnwelcome newes commonly renders the meſſenger unacceptable; and when we are diſpleaſed with the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, we frowne upon the deliverer. An ill plea it is (I confeſſe) for my ſelfe, ſince the ſubject of my inſuing Tract muſt be that which is generally cried downe by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, <hi>Obedience.</hi> But he that for feare of diſpleaſing, neglects his commiſsion, muſt undergoe a cenſure for his effeminate fearefulneſſe. To you therefore (my beloved auditors) muſt I preach the words of this great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles, Obey,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whom ye muſt <hi>obey,</hi> ye have already heard. How ye muſt <hi>obey</hi> comes now to be handled.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Obedite, &amp; obſecundate,</hi> ſay <hi>Tremellius</hi> (out of the Greek) and <hi>Stephanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Parete, &amp; obſecundate,</hi> ſayes <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Obedite &amp; auſeultate,</hi> ſayes <hi>Tremel.</hi> out of the <hi>Syriac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2046:8"/>4 <hi>Parete gubernatoribus veſtris, &amp; eſtote dictis illis obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes:</hi> ſo <hi>Fabritius</hi> out of the <hi>Syriac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Obedite &amp; ſubjacete:</hi> So ſayes the vulg. Lat. <hi>Arias Montanus, Iohannes Benedictus Pariſienſis,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Parete, &amp; obſequimini.</hi> So <hi>Sebastian, Caſtalion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Parete, &amp; concedite.</hi> So <hi>Leo Iuda,</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hyper.</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius</hi> renders the reaſon why 'tis tranſlated <hi>concedite. Non ſolùm convenit illis parere</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>verùm etiam quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere, &amp; permittere, &amp;c.</hi> Since we know that 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble even for the worthieſt Divine to be ſo exactly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and his hearers ſo diſcreetly judicious, as that he may hope to give content to every one in all things: <hi>Alij cauſantur paſtorem non ſatis doctum, &amp;c.</hi> Some are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for their lives, ſome for their ignorance in Schoole-divinity; ſome for not being at all, and ſome for being too much (as they will have it) read in the Fathers; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is accuſed for one thing or another, whether juſtly, or unjuſtly, <hi>Propterea Apostolus cupit aliquid eis concedi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Cedite</hi> ſaies <hi>Pelican: primò enim obedientiam, deinde honorem illis deferri jubet.</hi> And he wants not his reaſon: <hi>Cedimus enim</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>&amp; nos ſubmittimus iis quos honore proſequimur, &amp; ſuperiores agnoſcimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Subjacete</hi> ſaies <hi>Ludovicus Tena:</hi> and that,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Non reſiſtendo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Non vos iis co-aequando; ſed potius reverendo, &amp; honorando ut ſuperiores.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 The Greek hath the firſt word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth <hi>oratione flectere,</hi> as <hi>Stephanus</hi> will tell you: whence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Suada</hi> is made the Goddeſſe of Eloquence: ſo that the Apoſtle requires us to harken to, and <hi>obey</hi> the doctrine of the <hi>Clergie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>credo</hi> (not of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for that's too narrow) and it ſignifieth (as ſaies <hi>Tertullian)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2046:9"/> obedientia humilem, ſubmiſſam, &amp; ſupplicem exhibere;</hi> yea, ſuch obedience as forbids all replying, or anſwering again.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">G. Eſtius <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Eſtius</hi> quotes <hi>Theophylact</hi> and <hi>Oecumenius</hi> for tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it <hi>Exactam obedientiam, ut ſi operibus illis ſerviendum ſit, non detractent:</hi> Such exact obedience, as (upon a good occaſion) denies not aſſiſtance by purſe or paines: For (ſayes he) the Greek word ſignifies <hi>locum dare; ſubmittere ſe; &amp; obſequiis ſubjectionem oſtendere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The varietie of theſe Verſions hath cauſed diverſitie of opinions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Fulgentius</hi> thus; <hi>Obedite quantum ad praecepta, ut faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis ea quae per eos praecipit eccleſia. Subjacete, ut reverentiam exhibeatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Hugo Cardin.</hi> thus; <hi>Obedite quantum ad praecepta: Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacete quantum ad correctiones, et diſciplinas.</hi> And he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes his interpretation of the latter by the authority of <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.3. where the Vulg. Lat. reades it, <hi>Si tetigerit quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam de immunditiâ hominis, &amp;c. ſubjacebit delicto, id est,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>poenae delicto competenti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Dionyſius Carth.</hi> thus, <hi>Obedite praepoſitis veſtris, eorum praecepta ſervando. Subjacete reverentiam exhibendo.</hi> And he confirmes it by our Saviours words in <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. <hi>He that heareth you heareth me, and he that deſpiſeth you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth mee.</hi> From hence <hi>Gorran</hi> gloſſes upon the words thus: <hi>Obedite, &amp;c. mandata ſua implendo. Subjacete reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiam exhibendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which although it be the ſame with the former; yet he grounds it upon another place of Scripture, <hi>viz. Col.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Children obey your parents in all things, for this is well pleaſing unto the Lord:</hi> where by <hi>parents</hi> he underſtands, our reverend <hi>ſpirituall parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Aquinas</hi> upon my Text obſerves, that a twofold dutie is required in us towards our ſpirituall overſeers. <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2046:9"/>1 <hi>Obedientia, ut ipſorum mandata impleamus:</hi> which he preſſeth by that, <hi>in</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Behold, to obey is better than Sacrifice; and to harken, than the fat of Lambes: Quia per victimas aliena caro, per obedientiam verò voluntas propria mactatur</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Gregory.</hi> Becauſe in ſacrifices the fleſh of others, but in obedience the will of our ſelves is made the oblation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Reverentia, ut eos honoremus tanquam patres &amp; ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſciplinam toleremus:</hi> to honour them as Fathers, and to ſubmit to their diſcipline. This he confirmes both out of the firſt of 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.13. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Whoſoever reſist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then ye ſee according to the generality, that two things belong as due from us to our <hi>Prelates,</hi> viz.
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Obedience</hi> to their <hi>doctrine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Obedience</hi> to their <hi>diſcipline.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The former is due to the whole <hi>Clergie</hi> in generall, who divide the word of truth aright; the latter, to thoſe in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular that <hi>have the rule over us.</hi> Vpon theſe two columnes I ſhall erect the fabrick of my inſuing tract: and firſt of the firſt; <hi>viz. Obedience</hi> to their <hi>doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Generall poſitions for the moſt part <hi>command</hi> our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe; and require not arguments to preſſe our aſſent. <hi>To harken to the Preacher</hi> then we know it our dutie; and even children by imitation forbeare a neglect. I hope there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that your religious approbation of this generall <hi>Theſis,</hi> will not need my induſtrie in the proofe of its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. It is <hi>Lippis, &amp; tonſoribus notum.</hi> Yet to ſatisfie the objections of a ſcrupulous conſcience; and to correct the petulancie of refractory diſturbers, I ſhall firſt lay downe the qualitie of the perſons to whom we muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: ſecondly the manner of attention, and obedience we are to performe unto them. And firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2046:10"/>
            <p>The <hi>Eye</hi> and the <hi>Eare</hi> are the darlings of the world, and outſtrip the reſt of the ſenſes in their generall credit. Thus it is the cuſtome to skan our <hi>Miniſters</hi> by their <hi>precepts</hi> and <hi>examples.</hi> They are both the <hi>Vbera,</hi> the dugs of the Church, through which the people ſuck their divinitie. That Church is therefore ſubject to cenſure, of which (in reſpect of theſe) we may take up that complaint in <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8. <hi>We have a little Sister, and ſhe hath no breaſts.</hi> 'Tis farre better where but one is dried up, ſo the other give milke, be it <hi>precept</hi> or <hi>converſation;</hi> although I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe even that caſe very dangerous. 'Tis fearefull for a Miniſter to bee criminall in either: Yet for thoſe which have not the gift of <hi>preaching,</hi> our holy Church hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a learned ſupply in the Books of <hi>Homelies:</hi> but for the other ſhe cannot provide any remedie but by <hi>diſcipline.</hi> Ye have heard of the Law-givers anſwer; who being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded why he appointed no law for the puniſhment of a <hi>Parricide,</hi> replied, becauſe he never imagined that any wold be guilty of ſuch <hi>barbarous inhumanity.</hi> I hope the ſame too of our Eccleſiaſticall brethren, that <hi>none will be guilty.</hi> I ſhall onely therefore put you in mind (my reverend and moſt affected brethren) of that of S. <hi>Gregory; In exemplum culpa vehementer extenditur, quando pro reverentiâ ordinis peccator honoratur.</hi> He's yet more tart; pleaſe you to heare him ſpeaking to them eſpecially who are placed in authority; <hi>Scire debent Praelati quod tot mortibus digni ſunt, quot exempla perditionis ad ſubditos tranſmittunt.</hi> Or if you pleaſe to have a ſhorter <hi>memento,</hi> take that of S. <hi>Hier. Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis dignitas Sacerdotum, ſed grandis ruina ſi peccent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let me not forget my ſelfe. Come I here to queſtion the Prieſt, or rather to admoniſh the people? The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer I refer to our judicious Conſiſtories; the latter is the buſineſſe that's now to be handled.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2046:10"/>
            <p>'Tis a common deluſion of the deceiving Serpent to whiſper into the <hi>Laity</hi> a contempt of the <hi>Clergie.</hi> Alaſſe, alaſſe, 'tis too frequent; for we often ſee, that their falſe accuſations render him obnoxious, whom they deſire to have ſo. The rude vulgar ſit in judgement upon their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours,</hi> and condemne them for their innocency. Should their verdicts paſſe, Religion would become retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade; and he ſhould be accounted wicked who refuſeth to bewicked. They ſtrive upon a curious inquiſition to make him culpable; and upon the leaſt diſcovery of the ſmalleſt imperfection, they voice him ſcandalous. This (I am ſure) is not the effect of religious <hi>obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The interlineall Bible upon our <hi>Obedite,</hi> tels us in a marginall note, <hi>Praecipimur non diſcutere vitam praeſidenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; nam qui illos ſpernit Deum ſpernit.</hi> The inquiſition into the lives of them that <hi>have the rule over us,</hi> ought not to be the buſineſſe of thoſe that are of the <hi>Latty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. Arb. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Arboreus</hi> goes farther. <hi>Non ſatagere debent ſubditi, &amp; curioſè diſquirere num ſui Domini, &amp; praefecti honeſtè an turpiter vivant, modo eis recta, &amp; honeſta praecipiant.</hi> Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours are preſumptuous, if inſtead of attention to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, they pry into the converſation of their ſpirituall ſuperiours. <hi>Si benè dixerimus vestrum eſt; ſi benè vixeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nostrum eſt,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Augustine:</hi> our wholeſome doctrine benefits you; but our godly lives are advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to our ſelves.<note place="margin">S. Chryſ. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> Which puts me in minde of anſwering a queſtion propounded by S. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> and others; <hi>Whether the doctrine of a Miniſter may be neglected, where his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is to be blamed? Haymo</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haymo</hi> in locum.</note> that we owe obedience to them, <hi>In quantum doctrina, &amp; mores illorum ſancta, &amp; pia exiſtunt;</hi> ſo long as their doctrine is orthodox, and their lives unreproveable. But yet (ſayes he) <hi>Si à viâ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitudinis aberrent, non faciamus qualia agunt, ſed qualia
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2046:11"/> dicunt, &amp;c.</hi> If their lives be tainted, let us follow their precepts, and decline their practiſe. And he grounds it upon our Saviours ſpeech, as it is in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.2. and 3. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire: all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve, and doe; but doe not ye after their workes. <hi>Anſelme</hi> (quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Ludovicus Tena</hi>) is of the ſame opinion, that the enormities of the perſon ought not to bring contempt to his doctrine: <hi>Subjacete praepofitis</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>non tantùm bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; ſanctis, ſed etiam peccatoribus. Nazianzen</hi> will tell you, that although the Signet be Lead, or Iron; yet it will leave the ſame impreſſion as another of Gold. S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> will tell you, that the water which paſſeth through an earthen Pitcher, refreſheth the Herbs, as well as if the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell were made of Silver. Heare then S. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; <hi>In cauſâ fidei dum praepoſitus malignus extiterit, fuge illum, &amp; evita, non ſolùm ſi homo fuerit, ſed etiam ſi Angelus de Coelo deſcenderit. Si verò in vitâ moribus malignum dicis, noli curioſus eſſe, &amp;c.</hi> In matters of faith if he prove erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous decline him; yea, though he were an Angell from Heaven: but be not too quick-ſighted into the affaires of his life. <hi>Hiſce etiamſi dyſcoli ſint, &amp; ſcelerati, obediendum eſt,</hi> ſaies <hi>Theophilact:</hi> Their impurity muſt not detract from your <hi>obedience:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> Ser. <hi>5.</hi> ad fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres in ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. De obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiâ ad Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſuos. <hi>S. Chryſ.</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Gal. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> but it muſt be with S. <hi>Aug.</hi> his diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Non quia mali ſunt, ſed quia bona obſervare praecipiunt, quibus obedire debemus.</hi> Your obedience muſt be founded upon the purity of their preaching; not the impurity of their manners. S. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> determination in an other place is good; <hi>Si qui praeſunt improbi forent, innumeriſque ſcaterent malis, ne ſic quidem fas eſſet diſcipulo dictis non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientem eſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Though they that are ſet over you ſhould ſwarme with impieties, yet it freeth you not from attending to their wholeſome admonitions. But with that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2046:11"/> take the limitation of <hi>Eraſmus; modò ne pertrahant ad impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatem;</hi> ſo they ſeduce not to evill. Or with that of <hi>Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingius; Sit regula vox Euangelii, &amp;c.</hi> Let the Goſpell be their rule, againſt which if they preach, ye are freed from obedience to their doctrine in that particular. His ground for it is that of <hi>Cornelius</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 10.33: Now therefore we are all preſent before God, to heare all things that are commanded thee of God. <hi>Anſelme</hi>'s opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is the ſame; <hi>Obedite, id eſt, obtemperate juſsis eorum in omnibus, niſi fortè malum aliquod juſſerint, &amp;c.</hi> But he goes yet further, <hi>ſed caetera omnia, etiamſi non videantur eſſe bona, &amp;c.</hi> Obey their commandements ſo far as they are good; yea, even in things which at the firſt appearance ſeeme not to be good. Wherein me thinks he gives a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret check to thoſe whoſe too too ſcrupulous conſciences make them ſo ſuperciliouſly ſtrict, and ſo haughty mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that their owne opinions (though never ſo erronious) muſt ſit in judgement upon the actions of their Miniſters. They will be cenſurers, though their judgements are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved; which makes <hi>indifferences</hi> appeare to them ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Their forward cenſures hurrie them into errours; and their preſumptuous ſelfe-conceitedneſſe is the ground of their diſturbances. They are out of the way, and yet they had rather to nuzzle themſelves in an errour, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo wiſe as to acknowledge their folly. Too many alas of theſe does our countrey labour of: moſt of whom (for feare they ſhould be convinced of their opinions, and ſo become zealous with ſobriety) have quit our countrey to flie into their <hi>Canaan.</hi> Thus <hi>timor addidit alas,</hi> the feare of conformity hath made them to uſe the wings of their ſhips: and (as if they were begotten for rebellion) their ſpirits of contradiction diſdaine the confines of our flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing kingdomes. But for my part I ſhall wiſh them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2046:12"/> a proſperous gale to carry them to their Port; <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigent Anticyras,</hi> ſo we be no more troubled with their ſchiſmaticall cenſures, and clamorous diſturbances. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things in themſelves doe in a manner alter their nature when they are commanded by authority. It is the tenent of our<note n="*" place="margin">Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions &amp; Canons ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical; <hi>Can. 30.</hi> in ſin. Things of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, do in ſome ſort alter their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when they are either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or forbidden by a lawfull Magiſtrate: and may not be omitted at every mans plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, contrary to the Law when they be commanded; nor uſed when they are prohibited.</note> Church, and it ſhall ever be mine. I will therefore obey even in ſuch things, <hi>Etiamſi non videantur eſſe bona:</hi> for my particular judgement ſhall never juſtle the authority of ſo many reverend Divines, nor a private ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cineſſe oppoſe the learned acts of a judicious <hi>Convocation.</hi> I confeſſe that I cannot chuſe but take notice of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>God</hi> upon theſe ſchiſmaticall <hi>Preciſians:</hi> for whom ſpiritual pride hath puffed up into a ſchiſme in our Church, a ſeduced judgement baniſhes into ignorance of their temporall bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The <hi>quality</hi> of the perſons to whom ye are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to yeeld obedience, ye have already heard: The <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of our <hi>obedience</hi> followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> Ser. <hi>7.</hi> ad fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres in ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Obedientia ſine diſcretione caſſa eſt, &amp; vana,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine: Obedience</hi> without diſcretion is vaine: but he tels you how, <hi>non ex parte obedientis, ſed praecipientis;</hi> not in him that obeyes, but in him that commands. That lights upon him that is the author of the edict; and not upon the conſcience of him that's obedient. <hi>Tho. Aquinas</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth of a threefold obedience,<note place="margin">T. Aquin. 2a. 2ae. <hi>q.</hi> 104. <hi>art</hi> 5.</note> which I may apply to that which is due to the Fathers of our Church: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Sufficiens ad ſalutem:</hi> That which is ſufficient to our ſalvation; which bends in humility unto what it ſtands ingaged.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2046:12"/>2 <hi>Perfecta; quae obedit in omnibus licitis:</hi> ſuch as is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant only about ſuch things as are lawfull.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Indiſcreta, quae etiam in illicitis obedit:</hi> ſuch as queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not the lawfulneſſe of the thing commanded; but by a too <hi>facile,</hi> and un-man'd diſpoſition, yeelds in obedience to matters unjuſt. Now whereas in another place after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſame * <hi>Schoole-man</hi> queſtions;<note place="margin">T. Aquin. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2ae. <hi>q.</hi> 186. <hi>art.</hi> 4</note> 
               <hi>Vtrum obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia pertineat ad perfectionem religionis?</hi> Whether obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence concurs to the perfection of Religion? His concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is affirmative: <hi>Non quaſi indigentes dirigi ad perfectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem acquirendam; ſed quaſi per hoc ſe conſervantes in eo quod ad perfectionem pertinet.</hi> Should I engliſh <hi>Aquinas</hi> I muſt make uſe of the diſtinction betweene <hi>Incipiens, Proficiens,</hi> and <hi>Perfectus,</hi> before I ſhould render ſatisfaction to ſome curious inquiſitors; and in concluſion (for ought that I know) they might prove as captious. I ſhall leave them to their frowning opinions; and conclude this point with S. <hi>Bernards</hi> determination; <hi>Verus obediens mandata non procraſtinat; ſed ſtatim parat aures auditui, linguam voci, pedes itineri, manus operi, &amp; ſe totum intus colligit ut man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum peragat imperantis.</hi> The obedient Chriſtian upon his firſt command devotes himſelfe wholly to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of his command.</p>
            <p>I have done with your <hi>obedience</hi> required to the <hi>doctrine</hi> of the reverend <hi>Clergie,</hi> implied in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>obey.</hi> I come now to your obedience required to the <hi>diſcipline</hi> of the Church, included in the other word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſubmit your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Ex malis moribus bonae naſcuntur leges:</q>
            <p>badneſſe of conditions procured the goodneſſe of Lawes. <hi>Vt quos natura ipſa in officio retinere non poterat, ij magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2046:13"/> poenae à maleficio ſubmoverentur,</hi> ſayes <hi>Marc. Tul. Cic.</hi> that puniſhment might ſupply the defects of nature. What was the ground of our Lawes, is the ground likewiſe of our <hi>obedience:</hi> for (ſayes <hi>Iohannes Arboreus) Nos propter peccatum alijs hominibus ſubjecti ſumus.</hi> Sin brought in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: <hi>Nam natura omnes aequales genuit; ſed inaequalitas quae acceſsit ex vitio, est ordinata ex Dei judicio, unde nos opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet obedire hominibus:</hi> for nature intended an equality at our generations; but the pravitie of our diſpoſitions was the cauſe of inequality in our perſons. No marvell then that the Church may not want her <hi>diſcipline,</hi> when ſo many of her members will not want their defaults. Our Apoſtle not ignorant of the need of power in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall governement, inſinuates the neceſſity in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to <hi>ſubmiſsion: And ſubmit your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But durus eſt hic ſermo.</hi> Diverſe will better reliſh our doctrine than our <hi>diſcipline,</hi> and will be content to <hi>obey</hi> ſo they may not <hi>ſubmit.</hi> Miſerable men as they are, they would faine go to Heaven, but they are loth to ſtoope low enough to enter in at the gate. Did they but conſider, or propoſe unto themſelves the true and juſt ends of <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſsion,</hi> I preſume their depraved judgements would eaſily condeſcend to the neceſſity thereof. Let <hi>Hemmingius</hi> tell them of his twofold end thereof: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Vt honeſtâ, &amp; gravi diſciplinâ politeia eccleſiaſtica gubernetur:</hi> for the governement of the Church by grave and religious <hi>diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Vt obtemperantes miniſtris Dei, conſequamur promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam immortalitatis gloriam:</hi> that by our <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> we may inherit the promiſed crowne of immortality.</p>
            <p>Well then, we muſt not only be obedient to the <hi>precept,</hi> but alſo ſubject and conformable to the <hi>government.</hi> Yea, moreover (if <hi>Ludovicus Tena</hi> may ſpeake) <hi>Non tantum in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2046:13"/> his quae ſunt de jure divino, ſed etiam in his quae ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt de humano; quorum obſervantia paci, &amp; tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati eccleſiae expediat; vel ad mores bonos aliquo modo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat, ſaltem ex parte finis, licêt res de ſe ſit indifferens:</hi> not only in things directly commanded in ſacred writ; but alſo even in things which are added by the <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers;</hi> conducing either to the peace of the Church, or to the good behaviour of men; yea, though in themſelves the things be indifferent.</p>
            <p>If this be true (as no man I am ſure can juſtly deny it) what ſhall we account of the impudent diſturbers of the <hi>Hierarchie</hi> of our Church? What, not a <hi>Biſhop</hi> to governe? Shall their <hi>Lay-Elders,</hi> forſooth, (ſuch as the <hi>Elder Church</hi> never dream'd of) and their <hi>handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft-ſticklers</hi> in eccleſiaſticall matters, uſurpe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that belongs to the <hi>Prelates?</hi> Alaſſe (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) ye know 'twas <hi>Plato's</hi> determination touching Common-wealths, <hi>Tum demum fore beatas res publicas cùm aut reges ſaperent, aut ſapientes intelligerent:</hi> that they'd then beſt flouriſh when Kings grew wiſe; or wiſe men Kings: and ſhall it not hold ſo too in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline? Muſt a <hi>Dictator ab aratro</hi> be preferred before a learned <hi>Doctor in divinitie?</hi> Muſt we neglect the Vniverſities to rely upon <hi>Enthuſiaſmes?</hi> Away with theſe ſchiſmaticall diſturbers of our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull Mother. Shall our moſt reverend Clergie have all the labour, and ſhall their requitall bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but mallepert diſobedience?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> in loc. Paſtoribus er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go non tantum obedientia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur, ſed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am honor.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe determines, that <hi>honour</hi> of duty belongs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> tels us, <hi>Parendum eſt ei tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Deo qui nobis eſt vice Dei, in iis quae non ſunt apertè contra Deum.</hi> We muſt ſubmit to him as God, who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2046:14"/> is placed over us as God, in all things not directly contrary to the word of God. And who is that, but (in, and over both Church and Common-wealth) our gracious and dread Soveraigne: under him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately in the Church the moſt reverend Arch-biſhops: and ſo deſcending to every particular, and Parochiall Prieſt? Every ſuch particular Rectour of a Pariſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives that command from God which we finde in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.29. Keepe theſe men; if by any meanes they ſhall be miſſing, then ſhall thy life be for theirs: and ſhall they have no reſpect; yea, though they are the moſt inferiour of the Apoſtles? Yes doubtleſſe, or elſe when God ſhall queſtion them in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.20. Where is the flock that was given thee, that beautifull flock? If they reply, that they were loſt through their owne <hi>diſobedience,</hi> God will certainly ranke them among the Goats, which ſhall be ſeparated from the Sheepe. 'Tis true that <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus Faber Stapulenſis</hi> tels us of ſome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac. Fab.</hi> ſtap. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ſuis non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigilant, quia ſui non obediunt;</hi> who neglect their flocks, becauſe they neglect their <hi>obedience:</hi> but he concludes, <hi>hi inutiles ſunt gregi, &amp; grex illis;</hi> theſe are unprofitable to their flocke, and their flocke to them. The argument then holds currant, <hi>A minore ad majus:</hi> If Parochiall diſcipline requires ſubmiſſion in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners to their particular Paſtor; ought not much more both Sheepherds and Sheepe, both Prieſt and People, to ſubmit with all reverence and humility to Epiſcopall, to Provinciall diſcipline? The crimes of our age are too epidemicall to give me leave to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my ſelfe with a beliefe of a generall integrity, and concionable, lowly <hi>obedience.</hi> I know that among us
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2046:14"/> are diverſe of Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, unruly, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly perſons, ſuch as hee found among the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.14. Yea, and of his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as hee complaines of in the firſt of <hi>Titus, verſ.</hi> 10. But let his command be fulfilled, <hi>Warne them:</hi> and if that will not ſuffice; ſhall authority ly languiſhing in deſpare of redreſſe? Shall the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting oppoſition of head-ſtrong perverſeneſſe, foile the juſtice and pre-eminency of power? Nay rather let the ſharpeſt edge of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline make an inciſion, than the gangrene bee ſuffered to run into an univerſality.</p>
            <p>The time is ſpent. I ſhall conclude in a word of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Firſt to you (my reverent and learned brethren) I muſt crave leave to addreſſe my ſelfe, not for your information, but your remembrance. <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> and <hi>Submiſsion</hi> in the inferiours, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly grounded upon the examples of their betters. Yee know your Obligations to <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall</hi> juriſdiction: let mee beg your continuance in the practiſe, for I doubt not your ſubſcription. If the Sunne bee eclipſed, the whole hemiſphere is obſcured. Let your burning Tapours light the Laity to a ſight of their duty; and your care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practiſe invite them to <hi>ſubmiſsion.</hi> Your <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall obedience</hi> requires your obſervance; and your ſacred functions will challenge imitation. For mine owne part, if I am too young to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, I am not too old to learne. Your graveſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſhall make mee travell in your religious
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2046:15"/> ſteps; and your learned precepts ſhall make me your diſciple.</p>
            <p>To you (my beloved of the Laity in generall) I ſhall preſcribe the duty of <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſsion,</hi> ſuch as yee have heard mee allready treate of. Correct the fury of your unhallowed vices; and trace the way which your Divines preſcribe you. Let their <hi>diſcipline</hi> bee your governement; and their <hi>doctrine</hi> your practice. So ſhall your <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> be crowned in the end with joy, and your <hi>obſervance</hi> with eternall reward.</p>
            <p>To you in particular (who are elected the <hi>Guardians</hi> of your ſeverall Pariſhes) I muſt preach both <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>diligence.</hi> Remember that GOD whom yee called upon to witneſſe the promiſe of your fidelity. The enormities of your Pariſhes are your owne particular crimes, if yee proceed not legally in your juſt preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Yee remember your oathes; and yee know the puniſhment provided for <hi>perjurie;</hi> wherefore let him that hath <hi>eares</hi> heare. <hi>Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is a <hi>Traytour,</hi> and <hi>favour</hi> is a <hi>Paraſite: briberie</hi> is deceitfull, and <hi>neglect</hi> is damnable where they win the perſon to abrogate his oath. Your <hi>cauſe</hi> is juſt; feare not <hi>detraction:</hi> your <hi>oathes</hi> are religious; vallew not the <hi>envious:</hi> yee are ſupported by power; ſhake not at <hi>affronts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus if every one of us performe our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, our conſciences will bee our continuall Feaſts. If wee all joyne in <hi>obedience,</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to the powers below, for the ſake of him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2046:15"/> who ſitteth above, our lives ſhall bee free from diſtractions here; and our deaths ſhall open to us the gate of eternity. Even ſo, O God of Heaven, guide us whileſt we live in this valley of teares; and afterwards receive us into our Maſters joy. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 9. line 6. for <hi>Latins,</hi> reade <hi>Latine.</hi> p. 12. l. 20. f. <hi>here</hi> r. <hi>heare.</hi> p. 15. l. 32. <hi>credo</hi> r. <hi>cedo.</hi> p. 17. l. 27. <hi>notum</hi> r. <hi>nota.</hi> p. 19. l. 13. <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineall</hi> r. <hi>interlineary.</hi> p. 22. in marg. 2a. 2ae. r. 1. 2ae.</p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:2046:16"/>
            <p>erlegi hanc concionem, cui Titulus <hi>Obedience and ſubmiſſion, &amp;c.</hi> quae continet folia <hi>15.</hi> in quibus non reperio aliquid bonis moribus aut ſanae doctrinae contrarium, quò minùs cum utilitate imprimi queat: Sub ea tamen conditione, ut, ſi non intra tres menſes proximè ſequentes typis mandetur, haec licentia ſit omnino irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guilielmus Haywood,</hi> Cap. domeſt. R.P.D. Archiep. Cantuar.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2046:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
